Morton J. Savada Papers
Morton J. Savada Papers
circa 1920-2007
1990-2005
Savada, Morton J.
6 linear ft.
Papers from Savada's New York City business, Records Revisited, which dealt in 78rpm phonograph records. Includes correspondence from customers, other dealers, friends; inventories and receipts; obituaries, clippings, and other information about artists of the era.
2686914
Biographical History
Morton J. Savada (1923-2008) was an American record collector and dealer in New York City. He operated his business, Records Revisited, in midtown Manhattan for more than thirty years,
Savada was born in Manhattan and graduated from Cornell University with a degree in electrical engineering. He worked for the family business -- Savada Brothers Inc., a clothing company -- for twenty years before opening Records Revisited. The store specialized in 78rpm records from artists such as King Oliver, Ma Rainey, Artie Shaw and Benny Goodman, and carried genres ranging from big band and jazz to Latin, country, and spoken word. Although the store was a business, Savada also regarded the 250,000 albums on its shelves as a collection or archive; rather than sell the last copy of a recording he would make a copy on tape, and often loaned copies to CD producers or for use in movie sound tracks. For many years the store was a meeting place for Record Research, a group of about a dozen collectors and researchers.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Morton J. Savada Papers consists almost exclusively of material relating to Savada's record store, Records Revisited.
Correspondence-subject files contains correspondence from long-time customers, other collectors, and a few friends and family members. Financial files contain several years' worth of receipts, and sales tax exemption and resale certificates. The bulk of Lists and inventories is made up of Savada's inventory cards, alphabetized by artist name. Also included are photocopies of some discographies by label, a complete listing of Army V-Discs, morale boosters put out during World War II, and assorted other lists. Memorabilia contains Savada's desk calendars for 2003-2006, the business certificate for Records Revisited, and business cards for same as well as for Savada Brothers Inc. Printed material contains some very early items, such as the label from a Columbia Graphophone, as well as much later items such as newsletters and a concert program.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Separated Material
The complete inventory of 78rpm phonographs was donated to the Belfer Audio Archives at Syracuse University as the Morton J. Savada 78 RPM Collection. Please contact the repository listed above for more information.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Music; Popular culture; Connor, D. Russell (Donald Russell); Hicks, Warren W.; Savada, Morton J.; Records Revisited.; BG on the record: a bio-discography of Benny Goodman, D. Russell Connor and Warren W. Hicks.; Record labels.; Sound recordings -- Collectors and collecting.; Sound recordings -- History.; Appointment books.; Business cards.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Discographies.; Inventories.; Obituaries.; Photographs.; Receipts (financial records); Collectors.; Merchants.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Morton Savada, 2008.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Abbott, Darrell (Box 1)
  - American Vintage Record Labelography (Box 1)
  - Andres, Jean-Louis (Box 1)
  - Arenberg, Marietta (Box 1)
  - Arie, Michael (Box 1)
  - Auctions
    - Bids (Box 1)
    - Wins en route (Box 1)
  - A, misc (Box 1)
  - Baker, Artie (Box 1)
  - Barron, Blue (Box 1)
  - Bash [29th Annual VJM Collector's Fair and Bash] (Box 1)
  - Bendick, Bill (Box 1)
  - Bert Block Orchestra (Box 1)
  - Bickley, George F. (Box 1)
  - The Blue Pages (Box 1)
  - B, misc (Box 1)
  - Cabaniss, Jeff (Box 1)
  - Carl Fenton Orchestra (Box 1)
  - Cathcart, Paul H. (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    See also Obituaries.
    - About Savada (Box 1)
    - Collectors and collecting (Box 1)
    - E-music (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, See also Obituaries (Box 2)
  - Coogan, Jackie, rare label photostats (Box 2)
  - Cornell University (Box 2)
  - Crawford, Ken (Box 2)
  - C, misc (Box 2)
  - Darnel, Allan (Box 2)
  - Diaz, Cristobal (Box 2)
  - D, misc (Box 2)
  - Eaton and Behnke collections (Box 2)
  - Eldman, Sol (Box 2)
  - Evans, Gil (Box 2)
  - Expert Stylus Company (Box 2)
  - E, misc (Box 2)
  - Feil, Morris (Box 2)
  - Fein, Harry and Rita (Box 2)
  - Ferency, Frank (D. Jurgens) (Box 2)
  - Film dubs (Box 2)
  - Fire safety manual (Box 2)
  - Florance, Frank (Box 2)
  - Forms, blank (Box 2)
  - F, misc (Box 2)
  - Gray, Christopher, New York Times (Box 3)
  - Gray, John B. (Box 3)
  - G, misc (Box 3)
  - Herman, Jules (Box 3)
  - H, misc (Box 3)
  - Inman, Bob (Box 3)
  - International Association of Jazz Music Collectors (Box 3)
  - Ishii, Osamu (Box 3)
  - Johnson, Richard (Box 3)
  - Joyce Record Club (Box 3)
  - Juke boxes (Box 3)
  - J, misc (Box 3)
  - Kalb, Hartwig (Box 3)
  - Klein, Dave (Box 3)
  - Korst, Bill (Box 3)
  - Kremer, Mike (Box 3)
  - K, misc (Box 3)
  - Lang, Bob (Box 4)
  - Library of Congress (Box 4)
  - Lippmann, Sidney (Box 4)
  - L, misc (Box 4)
  - Gordon MacRae Club (Box 4)
  - Mahlowe, Gerald (Box 4)
  - Malcolm-Smith (Box 4)
  - Mascia, Glen (Box 4)
  - McCalla, Roy (Box 4)
  - Metolius Music Company, See Joyce Record Club.
  - Military Bands (Fred Williams) (Box 4)
  - Miller, John (Box 4)
  - Morgan, Colin (Box 4)
  - Music Research Book Publishers (Box 4)
  - M, misc (Box 4)
  - Nale, Dennis (Box 4)
  - Nash, Joe (Box 4)
  - Nauck, Kurt (Box 4)
  - Newton, Graham, and Colin Bray (Box 4)
  - Norvo, Red (Box 4)
  - N, misc (Box 4)
  - Obituaries
    - A-M (Box 4)
    - N-Z (Box 5)
  - Ohman, Anders (Box 5)
  - Ono, Ted (Box 5)
  - O, misc (Box 5)
  - Parnell, Rick (Box 5)
  - Petko, Ernie (Box 5)
  - Pilcher, Frank (Roane's Pennsylvanians) (Box 5)
  - Pictures of artists, stamps, clippings, postcards, other images (Box 5)
  - Pirak, Tony (Box 5)
  - P, misc (Box 5)
  - Quilliam, Mark (Box 5)
  - Randolph, Marvin (Box 5)
  - Rangus, John (Xavier Cugat) (Box 5)
  - RCA Latin (Box 5)
  - Record collections purchased (Box 5)
  - Record labels, some original, some photocopies (Box 5)
    See also Coogan, Jackie and Scranton, E.L.
  - Record Research (Box 5)
  - Renard, Jacques (Box 5)
  - Rhythm and News Magazine (Box 5)
  - Rizzo, Pat (Box 5)
  - Roane's Pennsylvanians, See Pilcher, Frank.
  - Rust, Brian (Box 5)
  - R, misc (Box 5)
  - Savada, Elias (Box 5)
  - Savada, Shira (Box 5)
  - Schuster, Ira (Box 6)
  - Scott, Walter (Box 6)
  - Scranton, E.L., includes photocopies of many record labels (Box 6)
  - Shipping/packing instructions (Box 6)
  - Storage albums price quotes (Box 6)
  - Stoffer, George (Box 6)
  - Sturtevant, Roger (Box 6)
  - S, misc (Box 6)
  - Tapes made
    - Current (Box 6)
    - Permanent file (Box 6)
  - Taylor, Bruce (Box 6)
  - Thygesen, Helge (Box 6)
  - Tucker, Orrin (Box 6)
  - T, misc (Box 6)
  - UCLA Archives (Box 6)
  - U, misc (Box 6)
  - Vrzal, Otto, includes photographs (Box 6)
  - V, misc (Box 6)
  - Wank, Kenneth (Box 6)
  - Williamson, Tom (Box 6)
  - Wilson, Teddy (Box 6)
  - W, misc (Box 6)
  - Y, Z misc (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous names and addresses (Box 6)
    See also Memorabilia: Business cards, others.
  - Unidentified (Box 6)
- Financial files
  - Receipts, pre-2002 (Box 7)
  - Receipts, 2002-2006; 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Sales tax exempt and resale certificates (Box 7)
- Lists and inventories
  - Army V-Discs (Box 7)
  - Catalogs (other people's) (Box 7)
  - Inventory cards
    - Aaronson, Irving - Sherwood, Bobby (Box 8)
    - Shilkret, Jack - Zentner, Sy (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous genres (Box 9)
  - Lists
    - By artist (Box 9)
    - By label (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Musicals
    This material consists of several hundred forms containing detailed information on musicals that opened or played in New York City, including title, open/close dates, venue, ticket price, names (stars, writer, producer, author, composer, lyricist, etc.), and whether Savada attended. The forms are in two binders, but additional slips are laid in with other information such as a list of openings by year and occasional newspaper clippings.
    - Shows, 1968-1974; 1 volume (Box 12)
    - Shows, 1975-1979; 1 volume (Box 12)
  - Value charts (Box 9)
- Memorabilia
  - Address book (Box 10)
  - Business cards and letterhead, Savada (Box 10)
  - Business cards, others (Box 11)
  - Business certificate (Box 10)
  - Desk calendars, 2003-2006; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Notes (Box 10)
  - Photographs, includes photos from visit to Sony Studios (Box 10)
  - Record cleaners, ads on the back include Decca, The Ink Spots, RCA Victor (Box 11)
- Printed material
  - BG On The Record: A Bio-Discography of Benny Goodman, by D. Russell Connor and Warren W. Hicks, 1969; annotated, corrected, numerous handwritten slips and other information laid in (Box 12)
  - Pre-1950, includes Columbia Graphophone label, 1944 issue of "Jazz Impressions," old playbills and advertisements; few are photocopies (Box 10)
  - Post-1970, newsletters, program, sheet music (Box 10)